<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mene, tekel, perez, or, A little appearance of the hand-writing (in a glance of light) against the powers and apostates of the times. By a letter written to, and lamenting over Oliver Lord Cromwell. / By John Rogers. In this woful howre of his temptation, and of Sions sore pangs, and solemne appeals; and of the precious saints imprisonments and persecution for this most glorious, betrayed denyed, and crucified cause of Christ Jesus King of Saints and nations.</title>
            <author>Rogers, John, 1627-1665?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91936</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1811</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E231_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7990</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99873225</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99873225</idno>
            <idno type="VID">125687</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91936)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 125687)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 40:E231[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mene, tekel, perez, or, A little appearance of the hand-writing (in a glance of light) against the powers and apostates of the times. By a letter written to, and lamenting over Oliver Lord Cromwell. / By John Rogers. In this woful howre of his temptation, and of Sions sore pangs, and solemne appeals; and of the precious saints imprisonments and persecution for this most glorious, betrayed denyed, and crucified cause of Christ Jesus King of Saints and nations.</title>
                  <author>Rogers, John, 1627-1665?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 8, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June: 10. 1654".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Sources --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:125687:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:125687:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Mene, Tekel, Perez,</hi> OR, A little Appearance of the HAND-WRITING (In a Glance of Light) Againſt the Powers and Apoſtates of the TIMES. By a Letter written to, and lamenting over <hi>Oliver</hi> Lord <hi>Cromwel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> JOHN ROGERS.</p>
            <p>In this woful Howre of his Temptation, and of <hi>Sions</hi> ſore pangs, and <hi>Solemne</hi> Appeals; and of the precious Saints im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonments and perſecution for this moſt <hi>Glorious,</hi> betrayed denyed, and crucified <hi>Cauſe</hi> of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi>
            </p>
            <p>KING OF SAINTS AND NATIONS.</p>
            <q>
               <p>There ſin is written with a Pen of Iron, and the point of a Diamond (<hi>ungue ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantino</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) whiles there Children remember their Altars and Groves, <hi>again.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jer. 17.15.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Why do ye perſecute me, as God? and are not ſatisfied with my fleſh? oh that my words were now written! oh that they were printed in a Book! that they were graven with an iron pen in the Rock for ever! For I know that my Redeemer liveth, and that he ſhall ſtand in the latter end upon the EARTH, &amp;c.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Job 19.22, 23, 24, 25.</hi> &amp;c.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Heu pietas! ubi pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>a? proſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> o tempora! Mundi Fax: Veſper! prope Nox! ô Mora! Chriſte Veni! <hi>Sinite Virgam Corripientem ne ſentiatis Mailcum Conterent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rn.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:125687:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:125687:2"/>
            <head>A word by the way to the Reader,</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince the time that I was lately ſo <hi>illegally</hi> &amp; <hi>arbitrarily</hi> plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered (without any <hi>Cauſe</hi> ſhown or known) by this <hi>Vnrighteous</hi> (ſelf-created) <hi>pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> that is got uppermoſt. I have with the words of <hi>Jeremy,</hi> Ch. 20.8, 9. cryed out <hi>vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and ſpoyl! violence and ſpoyl! becauſe the word of the Lord is made a Reproach, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſion daily. Then</hi> I <hi>ſaid,</hi> I <hi>will not make men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion nor ſpeak any more in his name; But his word was in my heart as a burning fire ſhut up in my bones, and</hi> I <hi>was weary with forbearing, and</hi> I <hi>could not ſtay.</hi> But conſtrained in <hi>ſpirit</hi> wrote this <hi>Letter,</hi> yet ſeeing by ſeveral <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers</hi> I have aſſaied, and that ſeveral dayes together to get it <hi>delivered,</hi> and finding it ſo <hi>difficult,</hi> that it is <hi>doubtfull</hi> whither it be ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conveyed to him or no; you find it prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as the moſt <hi>probable means</hi> of having it preſented to his <hi>eye,</hi> for that many <hi>Flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:125687:3"/>are ready to <hi>run</hi> with the <hi>news</hi> to their <hi>Maſter,</hi> as <hi>v.</hi> 10. <hi>REPORT, ſay they, and wee will REPORT it, all my Familiars watched for my balting, ſaying peradventure he wil be inticed, and we ſhall PREVAIL againſt him, and take our REVENGE on him.</hi> Well, if they do ſo, welcome <hi>CROSSE of Chriſt!</hi> for my next Petition <hi>to thy Kingdom come!</hi> is <hi>thy will be done in earth as it is in heaven!</hi> yet who knows but this weak <hi>word</hi> may <hi>awaken</hi> him a little! For, <hi>Aegros, quos potus fortis non cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravit, ad ſalutem pristinam Aqua tepens revoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit,</hi> warm water hath ſometimes recovered <hi>men</hi> to their former health; but whither this doe or not, my <hi>Conſcience</hi> is (now) ſo well ſatisfied, my heart be refreſhed, and my <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſo warmed</hi> in the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of our <hi>dear (deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) Christ,</hi> that I hope to go on with <hi>Jerem.</hi> 20.11. <hi>For the Lord is with me, who is the terrible one; therefore my PERSECVTORS ſtall ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, they ſhall not prevail, but they ſhal be greatly aſhamed, for they SHAL not proſper</hi> (long) <hi>and their everlaſting Confuſion ſhall never be FORGOTTEN!</hi> this is the victorious, <hi>overturning,</hi> already, <hi>triumphing Faith of</hi> 100ds (Bleſſed be <hi>JEHOVAH</hi> beſides.)</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>JOHN. ROGERS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:125687:3"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>VVHile the ſouls of many of the Lords dear <hi>Servants</hi> (who ſit weeping over you) are in <hi>Travel,</hi> and ſtruggle for you in this hour of <hi>Temptation.</hi> I moſt humbly beg (as upon my knees) for your own Soule, and Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and for the poor afflicted Saints ſake, that you will but <hi>weigh</hi> theſe few Lines of our preſent <hi>Lamentation,</hi> in the ballance of your heart and <hi>Conſcience</hi> (one part of an hour which you may beſt ſpare and be moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> which (if the Lord, whom I ſerve) require it, I thinke I could as freely write with my <hi>Blood,</hi> as with <hi>Irke,</hi> in <hi>tears</hi> and <hi>gall</hi> of grief) O our bowels! our bowels! our hearts ake, and are pained within us, to hear the dolefull groans and cryes! tears! prayers! and ſolemne Appeals of godly people in the <hi>Nation</hi> round about to the <hi>Righteous Iudge</hi> of the whole <hi>Earth!</hi> which (doubtleſſe) will be <hi>Anſwered</hi> with a dreadfull <hi>Diſpenſation,</hi> and ſevere <hi>Decree</hi> upon thoſe that be found the <hi>Enemies</hi> to the Lord <hi>Ieſus,</hi> and his <hi>Exaltation:</hi> The <hi>Apprehenſion</hi> whereof hath ſo ceaſed upon my Spirit, that I ſhould ſinne (if ſome way or other) I gave you no <hi>notice</hi> thereof, for that your own perſon is (yet) ſo deare in our very ſoules, that <hi>Bowels</hi> of <hi>Affection</hi> are frequently ſeen to you in mourning, praying, and wraſtling for you (if poſſible) to recover you out of thoſe bottomleſſe <hi>Snar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> wherein you are ſo deeply <hi>inſnared</hi> by the evill Counſell of <hi>Paraſites,</hi> ſubtle and ſelfe ſeeking <hi>Flatterers, Dawbers,</hi> and <hi>Deceivers,</hi> who have not that lively <hi>Sence</hi> to the <hi>Lord Ieſus,</hi> his poor <hi>Saints,</hi> and <hi>Intereſt,</hi> nor yet to your <hi>Soule</hi> (ſo deſpately ingaged we humbly conceive) as we who are counted enemies for the <hi>Truths</hi> ſake (as the Lord will <hi>witneſſe</hi>) have: Of whom as 3 <hi>Phil.</hi> 18, 19 <hi>I have told you often, and now tell you againe even weeping, that they are enemies to the Croſſe of Chriſt, whoſe end is deſtruction, whoſe God is their belly, and whoſe glory is their ſhame, who mind earthly things,</hi> Jeremiah 9: verſ. 1.2. <hi>Oh that my head were waters, and mine eyes a Fountain of tears, that I might weep day and night for the ſlaine of the Daughter of my people, that I might leave my people, and goe from them; for they be all Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, an Aſſembly of treacherous men.</hi> I cannot ſpeak with you in perſon, therefore I beſeech you read theſe words, which our tears and prayers are the <hi>Embaſſadors,</hi> and Fore-runners of <hi>Mittamus pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es &amp; lachrymas cordis l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gatos (Cyprian)</hi> for that we havenot the leaſt grain of ill will, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred or malice (as ſome ſuggeſt and ſay) againſt any perſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, but only againſt the ſins and evil of this change of government, which God wil (and if Righteous we are ſure muſt) Judge and then, as once you ſaid in your <hi>Letter</hi> to the <hi>Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke of Scotland, God who knoweth us, will in his due time <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:125687:4"/>manifeſt whether we doe multiple theſe things as men, or doe we them for the Lord Chriſt and his poor peoples ſake. Wherefore</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 Be pleaſed (we beſeech you with <hi>weeping</hi> tears) to compare a little <hi>preſent tranſactions</hi> with former <hi>Ingagements,</hi> and with the <hi>Armies Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations,</hi> &amp;c. as that of <hi>Iune</hi> 14. 1647. in page 6. declaring that you tooke up <hi>Armes</hi> in <hi>Iudgement</hi> and <hi>Conſcience</hi> for the peoples <hi>Iuſt Right</hi> and <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Your own De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</note> and <hi>Reſolved</hi> to aſſert and vindicate them againſt all <hi>Arbitrary power,</hi> violence, and <hi>oppoſition;</hi> and againſt <hi>all particular parties, and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts whatſoever.</hi> So page 7. <hi>that it is no reſiſting of Magiſtrary, to ſide with thoſe juſt Principles being theſe upon which you aſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed the Parliament: And that the glory of God was not wanting in ſuch caſes to ſet a price upon ſuch proceedings, it being one witneſſe of God in the world to carry on a Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony againſt the injuſtice and unrighteouſneſſe of men: And againſt the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage of Governments, when corrupted and declining from the primitive and originall glory.</hi> So page 9. <hi>We are ſo farre from deſigning and comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to have an abſolute o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> arbitrary power ſig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed or ſetled for continuance in any PERSONS WHATSOEVER; at that (if we might be ſure to obtaine it) we cannot wiſh to have it ſo in the PERSONS of any,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Againſt abſolute Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. in one Perſon.</note>
               <hi>whom we (our ſelves) could moſt confide in, or who ſhould appeare moſt of our PRINCIPLES and Opinions, or whom we might have moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall aſſurance of, or intereſt in: but that the Authority of this Kingdome in PARLIAMENTS may ever ſtand and have its courſe as the ſupream power and truſt,</hi> with many other things in that <hi>Declaration.</hi> So in the caſe of the <hi>Army</hi> ſtated and propoſed by the <hi>Agents</hi> from <hi>Gilford, Octob.</hi> 9. 1647. page 4. <hi>We tooke up Arms in Iudgement and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience for the peoples Juſt Rights and Liberties, &amp; not as mercenary ſouldiers hired to ſerve an arbitrary power,</hi> So page 13.14. <hi>The people ſhall ſee we minded not our</hi> own intereſt,<note place="margin">For ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note>
               <hi>but the Good, Freedome, and Welfare of the whole Nation,</hi> which in the ſame <hi>page</hi> is <hi>declared</hi> particularly to be in new <hi>Succeſſive Elections</hi> of <hi>Supream Aſſemblies</hi> of <hi>Parliaments</hi> at <hi>Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ods</hi> of times, and that it ought not to be denyed them, this being ſo <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiall</hi> to their <hi>Freedome,</hi> that <hi>without it they are no better then SLAVES, that therefore it be inſiſted on ſo poſitively and reſolvedly, as not to RECEDE from it,</hi> So page 15. <hi>That PARLIAMENTS rightly conſtituted are the Foundation of our hopes of Right and Freedome to the people; that therefore the conſtant SVCCESSION</hi> of <hi>PARLIAMENTS be ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolvedly inſiſted on that a law PARAMOVNT be made for it. And wheras all power is originally and eſſentially in the people; and whereas their free choice or conſent by the Repreſentors is the only originall and foundation of all Iuſt GOVERNMENT, that it be inſiſted upon poſitively, that the ſupream POWER of the peoples REPRESENTORS in PAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIAMENT be forth with declared for, as their power to make LAWS, or repeal Lawes, and to call to account all Officers in this Nation whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</hi> So page 16. <hi>This ſupream and ſole Power in Parliament being the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:125687:4"/>thing againſt which the King contended, and which the people have defended with their lives, and therefore ought now to be demanded as the PRICE of their BLOOD.</hi> So page 17. <hi>The many oppreſſions of the people, and the danger of abſolute tyrannie were the occaſion of the expence of ſo much blood, ſo that the people have bought theſe their Rights and Freedomes by the price of blood, &amp;c.</hi> Since that the <hi>Remonſtrance of</hi> St. <hi>Albans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Right and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome where it lies.</note> 1648. pag. 14.15. The <hi>ſumme of the publick Intereſt of a Nation to COMMON RIGHT and FREEDOME (which has been the chief ſubject of our conteſt) and in oppoſition to TYRANNIE and INJVSTICE of KINGS or others we take to lye in theſe things following.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That all Matters of ſupream truſt or concernment to the ſafety and welfare of the whole, be in a common and ſupream Councell or Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> &amp;c</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the power of making Lawes, Conſtitutions, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and Affairs (for the preſervation and government of the whole) and of altering or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealing, and aboliſhing, and power of finall Iudgements concerning Warre or Peace, the ſafety and welfare of the people, and all civill things whatſoever, and the ſupream Truſt in relation to ſuch things reſt in that ſupream Councell of Parliaments. So as 1. the ordinary ordering and government of the people may be by ſuch Offices and Adminiſtrations, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and according to ſuch Lawes and Rules as by that Councell or Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative have been preſcribed or allowed, and not otherwiſe. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. That no extraordinary or ordinary powers (as above mentioned) may be exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed towards the people by <hi>ANY</hi> (as of right) but by that ſupream Councell or Repreſentative, nor without their advice and conſent, may any thing be impoſed on or taken from the people, or if it be otherwiſe attempted by <hi>ANY,</hi> that the people be not bound thereby but free. So <hi>page</hi> 16 That it may not be left in the wil of the <hi>KING,</hi> or any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular perſon whatſoever (ſtanding in their own Intereſt) to oppoſe, make void, or render ineffectuall ſuch determinations or proceedings. So <hi>page</hi> 21.22. Where any perſon is truſted with a limited power, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Laws to preſerve the Rights and Liberties of the people, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes of power to their hurt, or by the advantage of that power ſhall riſe to aſſume hurtfull powers, which they never committed to him, and indeed to take away all thoſe Foundations of Right and Liberty, of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe and Remedy, and to ſwallow up all in his owne abſolute will and power, to impoſe, take away, and deſtroy at pleaſure,<note place="margin">They fought againſt perſonall Intereſt.</note> &amp;c. Such perſon doth <hi>(ipſo facto)</hi> forfeit all that truſt and power he had, &amp;c. <hi>Further in p.</hi> 65.66. That ſatisfaction &amp; aſſurance be given that what they have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for againſt the King <hi>(which is our humble ſuit now)</hi> for which we have been put to ſo much trouble, coſt and loſſe of blood, hath been only for the Liberties and common Intereſt, and not for your perſonall Intereſt and Power; that there may be a ſound ſettlement of the peace, and future government of the Kingdome upon grounds of common Right and Freedom, as followeth.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:125687:5"/>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">For Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments Annuall or bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onnual.</note>1 That there be a certaine ſucceſſion of future Parliaments (Annuall or Biennuall) with ſecure proviſion, that none who have ingaged or ſhall ingage in warre againſt the right of Parliaments or Intereſt of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple therein, or have adhered to the enemies thereof may be capable of electing or being elected (at leaſt during a competent number of years) nor any other who ſhall oppoſe or not joyn in agreement to this ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and that it be declared that ſuch Repreſentatives have and ſhall have the ſupream Power and Truſt. Beſides [much more in theſe other <hi>Declarations</hi>] that upon the <hi>Armies</hi> march into <hi>Scotland,</hi> 1650. pag. 36. We found our hearts extraordinarily ſtirred up by the Lord to aſſiſt the Parliament againſt the <hi>KING</hi> being abundantly ſatisfied in our Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Conſciences, that we were called forth by the Lord to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentall, to bring about that which was our continuall prayer to God: <hi>viz</hi> the <hi>deſtruction of ANTICRIST, and the deliverance of his CHVRCH and people.</hi> And upon this ſimple account we ingaged, not knowing the deep Policies of worldly Stateſ-men, and have ever ſince hazarded our lives in the high places of the field againſt all the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers of this worke of Ieſus Chriſt. And having thoſe things ſingly in our eye, namely the <hi>DESTRVCTION</hi> of <hi>ANTICHRIST,</hi> and the advancement of the <hi>KINGDOME</hi> of <hi>JESVS CHRIST.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Againſt King, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, and for the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt.</note> So <hi>pag.</hi> 38.39. A ſecond warre more dangerous then the former was contrived a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us by them that hated us of this Army of <hi>England</hi> under the name of <hi>SECT ARIES,</hi> and a ſecond teſtimony was given from Heaven to juſtifie the Proceedings of his poor Servants, againſt the bloody Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian <hi>BROOD,</hi> though with the loſſe of many precious Saints; we were then powerfully convinced, that their purpoſe was to deale with the <hi>LATE KING</hi> as a man of blood, and being perſwaded in our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences that he and his <hi>MON ARCHY</hi> was one of the <hi>TEN HORNS</hi> of the <hi>BEAST</hi> ſpoken of in <hi>Revel.</hi> 17.12, 13, 14, 15. we being witneſſes to ſo much innocent blood of the <hi>SAINTS</hi> that he had ſhed in ſupporting the <hi>BEAST,</hi> and conſidering the lowd cryes of the <hi>SOVLES</hi> of the <hi>SAINTS</hi> under the <hi>ALTAR,</hi> we were extraordinarily caried forth to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire <hi>JVSTICE</hi> upon the <hi>KING.</hi> But if there be any that have taken Councell againſt the Lord and his Anointed, whom the Lord hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed to ſet up in the holy Hill of <hi>Sion,</hi> we are perſwaded the Lord has brought us as <hi>INSTRVMENTS,</hi> through which he will ſpeak to them in his wrath, and vex them with his ſore diſpleaſure; we deſire it may be known, we are not Souldiers of Fortune, &amp; are not meerly the <hi>SER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VANTS</hi> of men,<note place="margin">And for the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy of King Jeſus alone.</note> we have not only proclaimed <hi>JESVS CHRIST</hi> the King of Saints, to be our King by profeſſion, but deſire to ſubmit to him upon his own termes, to admit him to the exerciſe of his <hi>ROYALL AVTHORITY, and with much more to that purpoſe:</hi> yea, to name but one more (the <hi>Declaration</hi> of <hi>Aprill</hi> 22. 1653. <hi>pag.</hi> 6. After much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate it was judged neceſſary and agreed upon, that the ſupream Authority
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:125687:5"/>ſhould be by Parliament devolved upon known perſons, men ſearing God, and of approved Integrity, and the Government committed to them for a time, as the moſt hopeful I way to incourage, and countenance all Gods people reforme the <hi>Law,</hi> and adminiſter <hi>Juſtice</hi> impartially, hoping thereby the people might forget <hi>MONARCHY,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Againſt this Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy againe, and for Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> and underſtanding their true Intereſt in the Election of ſucceſſeſive <hi>PARLIAMENTS,</hi> may have the Government ſetled upon a true <hi>Baſis,</hi> without hazard to this Glorious <hi>CAVSE,</hi> or neceſsitating to keep up Arms for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the ſame. Though much more of the ſame import out of ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry other Letters and <hi>Declarations:</hi> We might produce, yet for feare of being too tedious) our ſoules would rejoyce, and be abundantly <hi>ſatisfied</hi> to ſee an <hi>Harmony</hi> between theſe <hi>Declarations,</hi> and the preſent <hi>Actions</hi> of this preſent Government, ſeeing (as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith) <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> 4.5. <hi>When thou voweſt</hi> (or art devoted or ingaged) <hi>to God deferre not to pay it: Better it is that thou ſhouldeſt not vow, then that thou ſhouldeſt vow and not pay, ſuffer not thy mouth to cauſe thy fleſh to ſinne, neither ſay thou before the Angell that it was an errour, wherefore ſhould God be angry at thy voice, and deſtroy the worke of thine hands: Oh! my Lord! let the blood, lives, and tears,</hi> be thought upon that have <hi>ſealed</hi> to theſe <hi>Declarations,</hi> and ingaged for <hi>Chriſt</hi> his cauſe: and the Liberties of the people by Parliaments, &amp;c. O be not offended with us whoſe ſoules mourn for theſe ſins and tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and are weaned (as then you would have us) from <hi>Monarchy,</hi> or any ſuch like <hi>GOVERNMENT!</hi> ſeeing in ſome of them (as in the <hi>Declaration, April.</hi> 2. 1653 and <hi>Iuue</hi> 14. 1647. <hi>page ult.</hi>) you preſſe it upon us to ſtand for theſe <hi>things,</hi> and you ſay you expect it of us, and of all that are well affected to the <hi>Publick,</hi> but now we are declared <hi>offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> for ſo doing! Oh dear! honoured Sir, what ſhall we ſay but your owne words in <hi>page</hi> 52. of the <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> of St. <hi>Albons.</hi> Your <hi>bare retracting or changing your cauſe (without better or any reaſons giving) can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not put out the light which your former Declarations with reaſons have let in, and which God hath ſo eminently owned and given his ſeale and increaſe unto.</hi> O my Lord! that theſe things might be cleared to the poor! un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfied <hi>people</hi> of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>! whoſe hearts are <hi>bleeding</hi> under the ſenſe of them day and night! <hi>Zedekiahs</hi> caſe and calamity for his breach of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> and his imbondaging againe the people after <hi>Liberty</hi> proclaimed and declared, <hi>Ier.</hi> 34 <hi>verſ.</hi> 15 16. <hi>And ye were now turned and had done right in my ſight, in proclaiming Liberty every man to his Neighbour, and yee had made a Covenant before me in the Houſe which is called by my name. But yee turned and polluted my name, and cauſed every man his ſervant, and every man his hand-maid, whom he had ſet at Liberty at their pleaſure, to return; and brought them into ſubjection, to be unto you for ſervants, and for hand-maids</hi> being often in our remembrance.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2 Be pleaſed (my Lord) a little to <hi>reviſe</hi> or <hi>reaſon,</hi> with the <hi>riſe</hi> of this <hi>change</hi> upon the breaking up the late <hi>Parliament,</hi> taking its being there,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:125687:6"/>(but for this end) to keep up the carnal <hi>intreſts</hi> the <hi>Parliament</hi> had voted down, <hi>viz</hi> of <hi>Clergy, carnal Church State, Tithes, Preſentations</hi> &amp;c. which was according to the ſeveral <hi>Declarations</hi> of the <hi>Army,</hi> as in the <hi>Caſe</hi> of the <hi>Army</hi> ſtated <hi>Octob</hi> 9. 1647. <hi>page</hi> 2.8.10. and <hi>Declaration</hi> of <hi>August</hi> 1. 1647. from <hi>Colebrook page</hi> 13. the 5 <hi>Propoſition</hi> is the preſent <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nequall, troubleſome, and contentious way of Miniſters maintenance by Tythes be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered of, and remedy applied; ſo the 6th: is that the Rules and Courſe of Law, and the Officers of it be reduced and reformed,</hi> and concerning the <hi>Clergy</hi> with then <hi>carnal Church State</hi> the <hi>Remonſt.</hi> of <hi>St. Albans page</hi> 10th. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares it the <hi>Parliaments part to take away theſe corrupted forms of outſide re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Church government,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> he Riſe of this G. up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of the laſt Parl. how? and why?</note>
               <hi>whether impoſed without law, or rootea in the law in times of Popiſh ignerance or idolatry or of the Goſpels dimmer light, by we ans whereof ſnares and chains were laid upon conſcientions and zealous men, and the generality of the people held in darkneſſe, ſuperſtition, and blind reverence of perſons and outward things fit for Popery and Slavery; and alſo to take away and loſen that dependance of the Clergy and their Eccleſiaſtical af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs upon the King, or that intereſt of the Clergy in the civil laws and affairs which the craft of both in length of time had wrought for each other; and that it was the Kings part to uphold and maintain this dependance of the CLERGY their MAINTENANCE and CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH MATTERS;</hi> and were it not too tedious, I ſhould name many more of your <hi>Declarations,</hi> againſt theſe very things: Now for the <hi>Parliament</hi> to do that which the <hi>Army</hi> and good people round the <hi>Nation</hi> have declared to be their <hi>duty, viz.</hi> to take off the <hi>civill dependance</hi> of the <hi>nationall Clergy,</hi> with their <hi>nationall Church St.</hi> and to vote a <hi>new model</hi> of the <hi>Law, viz</hi> leſſe intricate, uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, Tyrannical, and unjuſt, and more conſonant with Gods word, Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, and judgements, and right reaſon; and more plain, and eaſie, and clear. And to take away <hi>corrupt and ſimonious preſentations,</hi> whereby <hi>ſouls</hi> &amp; <hi>people</hi> are bought, and ſold to great mens luſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For this (formerly jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, their <hi>duty</hi> to be <hi>diſſolved</hi> and broken, yea at that time too (when this longed for mercy after many years was brought to the <hi>birth,</hi> by ſome <hi>faithfull ſervants</hi> of the Lord (precious round the Nation) after many <hi>pangs,</hi> much <hi>oppoſition,</hi> yea and after the long ſitting <hi>Parliament,</hi> was bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken too for their neglect of theſe very things (with others;) ſeems ſtrange to us,<note place="margin">Rev. <hi>18.13.</hi> being Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize of Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon.</note> and the more <hi>diſſatisfies</hi> us, for that we ſee this <hi>Power</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed for the ſupport and <hi>upholding</hi> of thoſe things which that <hi>Parliament</hi> had voted down; and which the <hi>Army</hi> and good <hi>people</hi> had ſo often <hi>decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi> prop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Antichriſt;</hi> this makes the <hi>Riſe</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it more grievous to the ſouls of ſome of the <hi>Saints,</hi> then in that the <hi>peoples choice</hi> was not in it, though ſomes <hi>Declarations</hi> required that alſo, 6. <hi>Micah</hi> 16. <hi>The Statutes of</hi> Ou ri <hi>are kept, and all the works of the houſe of</hi> Alab, <hi>and ye walk in their counſels, that I ſhould make thee a deſolation, and the inhabitants thereof an biſſing: therefore ye ſhall bear the reproach of my people.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:125687:6"/>
            <p>O my <hi>Lord,</hi> that the opening and bleeding of our <hi>Bowels</hi> for theſe things might be a little regarded and pittied!</p>
            <p n="3">3. May you be (moſt humbly as upon our bended knees) intreated to take a little <hi>account</hi> of the already <hi>fruits</hi> and effect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of this <hi>alteration,</hi> which (the Lord knows) we bitterly bewail before the <hi>great God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> The already effects &amp; fruits of this change, moſt grievous to the faithfull &amp; Godly</note> as more heavy to us, then the precedent <hi>changes</hi> in ſhutting up the dores of our <hi>publick meeting place,</hi> hindring us in Gods <hi>Worſhip;</hi> impriſoning our dear <hi>Brethren,</hi> &amp; <hi>friends,</hi> plundering reproaching &amp; grieving them (and them onely) that have been, all thoſe wars and yet are (and we hope ever will be) faithfull to the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> and <hi>Kingdome</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> threatning to take away their lives, and indeavouring to ſtone and ſtab them, aſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſing them with moſt <hi>palpable</hi> loathſome, and notorious <hi>falſities,</hi> to poſſeſſe good <hi>people</hi> in the <hi>Countries</hi> with <hi>prejudice</hi> agai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt them, as if they were againſt all <hi>Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> Miniſtry, and Property, which with a wonderous and wicked <hi>confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> ſome write and ſpread about (the Lord lay it ſeriouſly to their <hi>hearts</hi> and humble them for it!) but we cannot be ſuffered to <hi>Print</hi> the <hi>Truth,</hi> or to anſwer their cruell and unjuſt <hi>Calumnies</hi> or <hi>Accuſations,</hi> whileſt we deſire no other <hi>weapons,</hi> (the Lord knoweth) for our <hi>warfare,</hi> but the <hi>Word of Truth,</hi> (which ſhall be our defence!) yet we are not ſuffered to print, but plundered of our <hi>notes</hi> and writings, whiles all manner of <hi>lies,</hi> ſlanders, and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>njurious reports,</hi> are printed and divulged of us. This was counted Tyranny in the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and after in the <hi>Prelates,</hi> and declared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>page</hi> 10. of the Caſe of the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>my ſtated <hi>October</hi> 9th, 1647. <hi>viz</hi> [to lock up the Printing Preſſes, againſt whom they pleaſe was in the Biſhops time complained of, as one of the great oppreſſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] and yet (to hinder <hi>truth</hi>) it is now made <hi>Treaſon</hi> to print or preach it; ſo that we are forced to <hi>conceal</hi> truth from the <hi>world,</hi> and the <hi>witneſſes</hi> lie a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it were dead in the <hi>ſtreets,</hi> by ſuch <hi>Political combinations</hi> (as theſe are) who do all they can to keep out the breaking forth of that light and truth, which ſuits not with their preſent <hi>purpoſe;</hi> wherefore our onely <hi>remedy</hi> left us is <hi>faith and prayer,</hi> and ſolemn <hi>Appeals</hi> to him that judgeth <hi>righteouſly:</hi> yet the Lord ſhew mercy to our <hi>unkind brethren</hi> in the day of his <hi>appearing!</hi> And in the mean time <hi>declare</hi> whether they do well or no to <hi>cry</hi> out (ſo cruelly and rais;ly againſt us in this our <hi>new captivity</hi>) and to ſtir up the <hi>people</hi> againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s (as <hi>evil doers</hi>) by the advantage which they have in <hi>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> what they will againſt us, whileſt our hands are tied behind us, and truth is bound! Beſides oh! oh! are not men of <hi>corrupt principles</hi> and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal intereſt up again, with the higheſt confidence! <hi>malignants</hi> countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced? and ſuch incouraged as were (not long ſince) declaimed againſt? whileſt onely the little remnant of the Lords <hi>faithfull ones</hi> are frowned up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on! brow beaten! <hi>threatned!</hi> grieved! &amp; wounded to the very ſouls of them for theſe things! but our great comfort and confidence is, that in this <hi>Day</hi> which will burn as an <hi>Oven</hi> (when all the <hi>proud,</hi> and all that do wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly ſhall be as ſtubble) the <hi>ſon of righteouſneſſe</hi> ſhall ariſe with <hi>healings</hi> upon us.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:125687:7"/>
            <p n="4">4 Laſtly (my Lord) may you be pleaſed but to ſee a little in the midſt of our <hi>Agony</hi> and <hi>trouble,</hi> how l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke this preſent <hi>Government</hi> looks to that which the Lord (by the <hi>faith and prayers</hi> of his deſpiſed <hi>people</hi> 11. <hi>Heb.</hi> 33.) hath ſo eminently ingaged againſt, <hi>laid</hi> in the duſt, and <hi>ſtamped</hi> upon with diſdain (fullfilling his word therein) and whileſt you were with the Lord (therein) he was with you but oh! is there no danger to fit in the ſame <hi>ſeat?</hi> be under the <hi>Predicament?</hi> walk in the ſame <hi>Ways?</hi> keep up the ſame <hi>intereſts?</hi> with them that were (for example ſutely) ſo viſibly <hi>deſtroied</hi> and cut off. The <hi>former K.</hi> (cut off) had his <hi>Courts,</hi> Councels, <hi>State,</hi> Pride, <hi>Idleneſſe</hi> and vanity in perſons about him, <hi>rich beds,</hi> hangings, <hi>Coackes</hi> and <hi>Attendants,</hi> evill Councellors, <hi>Politicians,</hi> and wiſe men put him upon <hi>impriſoning,</hi> oppreſſing, and <hi>perſecuting</hi> the <hi>poor deſpiſed Saints,</hi> under the name of <hi>Deceivers,</hi> Hypocrites, and <hi>Fanatick ſpirits,</hi> &amp;c. that were not of the ſame <hi>principles</hi> with him, and his <hi>Court,</hi> ruling for his <hi>own intereſt,</hi> more then for the <hi>peoples Liberties, &amp;c.</hi> and (O my Lord) but a little conſider, is it not ſo in all or moſt of the ſame <hi>points,</hi> pleaded againſt him ſo long together, by the ſword, by the word and faith of Gods people,<note place="margin">How a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like this G. is to it which God hath thrown down be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes.</note> thouſands of whom loſt their <hi>lives</hi> and deareſt <hi>bloud,</hi> and <hi>friends</hi> to free us from all theſe things; O my Lord, make us not your <hi>enemies,</hi> by telling you the <hi>truth,</hi> with <hi>tears,</hi> and bleeding Bowels! (the Lord knows) for you and yours; whom the Lord hath ſo highly owned and honoured in his deſign againſt this very kind of <hi>G</hi>—. be pleaſed to uſe your own words, <hi>page</hi> 12.31: 38, 39. of the <hi>Declaration</hi> of the <hi>Army</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into <hi>Scotland,</hi> 1650. wherein you declare againſt any <hi>government</hi> by one man or <hi>K.</hi> unleſſe it be <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> and you tell the Brethren of <hi>Scotland,</hi> if they proceed in any ſuch <hi>deſign,</hi> to bring in ſuch a <hi>Government</hi> as <hi>King</hi> upon us, they will <hi>blot out not onely their former merits but undo the noble atchievements of the Engliſh Patriots and Parliaments in this &amp; former Generations:</hi> For we know (ſay you) <hi>how eaſie a thing it is to raiſe a Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chical ſpirit, but how hard it is to keep it within the circle,</hi> we know the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> &amp; old <hi>Plea</hi> is <hi>neceſſity;</hi> which, with ſound Chriſtians, cannot now ſatisfie as a competent Apology; for that <hi>Machivil</hi> hath ever made that a Cloak for his exorbitant actions;<note place="margin">Neceſſity no good Plea.</note> yea the <hi>Jews</hi> to <hi>crucifie</hi> Chriſt pretended thus, O <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> but (as one ſaid) there is no <hi>NECESSITY</hi> to ſin, but againſt it, and the <hi>Saints neceſſity</hi> in a <hi>civill reference</hi> (as well as ſpiritual) is to exalt <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>his Kingdome.</hi> But for this we onely flie to your own words again. [<hi>Remonſt. St. Albans page</hi> 5th. He that ingageth (upon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences for publick ends) and that upon publick neceſſity or extremity (all which ſay you muſt concur to their full ſatisfaction therein) he will firſt try all honeſt ways poſſible with due regard to, and concurrence with the preſervation of the Magiſtracy, and Government under which God hath ſet him, before he will flie to any ways of extremity, neither will he (when ingaged therein) proceed further or longer in that way againſt or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Magiſtracy, then that firſt neceſſity, or ſome other (emergent
<pb facs="tcp:125687:7"/>(upon the proceeding) does juſtly lead, not driving the pretence of Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, further to ſerve or advantage himſelf, or perpetuate thoſe ways of extremity) but when the neceſſity or danger is over, wil return again to <hi>Magiſtracy</hi> &amp; <hi>Order</hi> (<hi>i.e.</hi> now by <hi>Parliam.</hi> as before) we deſire no more then your own words. But ſeeing ſome of your <hi>Court</hi> do caſt in <hi>Reaſon of State</hi> (as well as <hi>neceſſity</hi>) for this <hi>Alteration,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reaſon of State dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous.</note> we wiſh (in the <hi>travel</hi> of our ſouls for them) that their eys were opened, to ſeethat this hath been, &amp; wil bethe <hi>ruin</hi> of al <hi>States</hi> &amp; <hi>Governors</hi> now in the world, <hi>viz.</hi> their <hi>Reaſon</hi> of <hi>State!</hi> carnall or <hi>worldly Policie</hi> and <hi>Wiſdome,</hi> this brought the <hi>blood of Iezreel</hi> on the houſe of <hi>Jebu</hi> (though he executed <hi>Juſtice</hi> on the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>houſe</hi> according to <hi>Gods command</hi>) yet he walked in the <hi>ſame wayes,</hi> gat up upon the <hi>ſame Throne,</hi> and into the <hi>ſame Kingdome,</hi> and kept up the <hi>ſame Intereſt!</hi> and Idoll worſhip his <hi>Predeceſſors</hi> (cut off by the hand of Juſtice) did, and did the worke but by <hi>halfes;</hi> and all by <hi>reaſon of State.</hi> This <hi>Reaſon</hi> rejected <hi>Saul,</hi> and made him diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent; this was that <hi>Reaſon</hi> that led <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Hoſt into the bottome of the <hi>Sea,</hi> in his bitter heat againſt the worke of God in that day; and this was that principle that made <hi>Sihon,</hi> King of the <hi>Amerites,</hi> and <hi>Og</hi> King of <hi>Baſhan, Num.</hi> 21. oppoſe <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the <hi>worke of God</hi> in that <hi>Generation</hi> to their lamentable <hi>ruin.</hi> Yet this was the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> principle and <hi>light</hi> that lead the <hi>grave Councell, John</hi> 11. into that <hi>curſed Vote</hi> of <hi>cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying</hi> Chriſt! And is not this <hi>warning</hi> enough for us? Then ſee in all <hi>Ages</hi> how the reſults of the pureſt <hi>reaſon</hi> of <hi>ſtate</hi> have proved <hi>dangerons,</hi> yea deſtructive to <hi>Governors</hi> and <hi>Governments,</hi> ever oppugning the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>worke</hi> and deſigue of God in theſe ages. Therefore O my Lord, let not this principle deceive you, leſt it deſtroy you! May I ſpeak <hi>Luthers</hi> words to you (in <hi>Epiſt. ad Melanst.</hi>) <hi>Sed ſcribe hee fruſtra, ſi tu ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum Philoſophiam veſtram, has res ratione regere, hoc eſt cum rations inſani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, perges &amp; occides to ipſum, &amp;c.</hi> I write theſe things in vaine if you will <hi>reſolve to Rule by Carnall reaſon,</hi> and according to the corrupt Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates and the <hi>Philoſophy</hi> of <hi>Sophiſters,</hi> about you, which if you do will fall inevitably, ſad to you one day, and too too probably, will prove, your Ruin, which we beſeech our God in <hi>mercy</hi> and <hi>time</hi> forbid. <hi>Ergo certe are prote &amp; dol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> te meas preces ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> irritas facere.</hi> Oh! make not our daily <hi>prayers</hi> for you of no <hi>effect</hi> to you; and becauſe many <hi>Good men,</hi> as well as <hi>Great,</hi> were preſtr'd by the <hi>pernicions</hi> Counſels and <hi>Suggeſtions</hi> of ſome <hi>Ambitioniſts</hi> and ſelſiſh Teachers, and <hi>Schollars</hi> in <hi>Luthers</hi> days, he was wont to pray, [<hi>a doctore glorieſe &amp; a paſtere contentieſe libera nos dominus,</hi> the Lord deliver us from ſuch glorions <hi>Rabbies,</hi> and ſelfe-ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contentions <hi>Teachers?</hi> And muſt we not pray that you may be freed from ſuch as have ſubtilly inſuared you,<note place="margin">Our Weapons of war far &amp; our adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries what they are</note> and doe <hi>Prelate like</hi> poſſeſſe you, and others againſt us? that we are <hi>Fanatique,</hi> mad men, <hi>Fools</hi> and heady <hi>enemies</hi> to Magiſtracy, Miniſtry, and all, &amp;c. for which our hearts are pained within us whiles we <hi>ponder</hi> theſe things, &amp; our <hi>ſpirits</hi> greived, that men, of ſo much former <hi>Merit</hi> and <hi>Eminency,</hi> ſhould ſo ſinfully, and <hi>unchriſtianlike</hi> condemne and <hi>accuſe</hi> us of thing our <hi>hearts</hi> abhorre, and loath within us: And call for <hi>ſeverity,</hi> under the name of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:125687:8"/>Perſecution againſt us in the matters of our <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Conſciences,</hi> meerly and alone for the <hi>exalting</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> in the things which they themſelves have formerly <hi>preached</hi> and <hi>profeſſed</hi> to others; yea, which the <hi>whole Army</hi> have frequently declared for many years together, till it came into <hi>Faſhion</hi> to hold an <hi>Epheram religionem,</hi> a Court Religion which will turne with the times! but the Lord humble and break us for it: But <hi>wiſdows</hi> (ſayes <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>is better then weapons of war, Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtes</hi> 9. and as we have ſo we <hi>deſire</hi> no other weapons but <hi>Gods owns word</hi> and ſpirit, having our <hi>Loines</hi> girt about with <hi>Truth</hi> and having on (bleſſed be our God for it) <hi>the Breſt plate of Righteouſneſſe in this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> wherein our Brethren are againſt us.</p>
            <p>But my Lord, may the preſented <hi>Truth (or poor crucified Jeſus)</hi> beg this favour to give it as much <hi>liberty,</hi> as his <hi>adverſaries</hi> have for their groſs <hi>lies</hi> and <hi>falſities,</hi> in <hi>printing</hi> or otherwiſe; therefore will you be pleaſed, (though but for a little time, a moneth or two) to releaſe thoſe laws that hinder the <hi>liberty</hi> of publiſhing the <hi>Truth,</hi> Let our Brethren or any that wil oppoſe, us convince, or corquer al they can <hi>with the good word of God,</hi> &amp; we ſhall be ſatisfied to try it out with them ſo; but not with the <hi>weapons of the world,</hi> as they have them (now) all on their <hi>ſide,</hi> to <hi>impriſon perſecute,</hi> or put to death, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for that is <hi>Antichriſts</hi> (not Chriſt) way of <hi>warfare.</hi> In this ſenſe (ſaies <hi>Luther in Epiſt. ad Erph.</hi>) <hi>conſider with what ſword I have conquerd ſin, and overcome errors, and ſubdued policy, I have never touched you with a finger, but with the ſpirit of Christs mouth,</hi> viz. <hi>the Word of his Goſpell,</hi> ſo <hi>Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inglius reſp, as Sirothin to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>. </hi> 2. <hi>fol.</hi> 302, <hi>declares</hi> the <hi>Word of God the mely inſtrument to overcome with, onica <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a que viaſola eſt,</hi> &amp;c. The word is the onely way to <hi>ſubdue errors;</hi> therefore, ſaith he <hi>we ſuffer all the writings of the Papiſts to be ſpread and read, for the ſword of the ſpirit ſhall deſtroy them all; what cauſe then,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>is more ſuſpicious then ours, who would have even the Adverſaries Doctrines publiſhea, that we may overthrow them with the word? or your who reproach us as hereticall and will not ſuffer ours to be publiſhed?</hi> this is our caſe now. Therefore as <hi>Luther</hi> wrote to the <hi>Dukes</hi> of <hi>Saxony, Epiſt. Tom</hi> 7. <hi>fol.</hi> 209, ſo do we humbly to you my Lord, <hi>I would not,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>but all have free Liberty, yet if any tranſgreſſe Goſpell bounds, and would raiſe up ſeditions or wars againſt you, then you may ſuppreſſe them.</hi> So, my Lord, if we ſtir up people <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ſings, tumults, or carnal warfare, as men falſly charge us, then puniſh us a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you pleaſe, for it is contrary to our <hi>principles</hi> ſo to do) but to the ſpiritual works and <hi>warfare,</hi> wherein we are now ingaged, <hi>viz faith and prayer.</hi> Furthermore O <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that you would not beleeve every report of the <hi>Ronti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ous or Fire-blowers</hi> of theſe our new troubles, againſt us. For as it was once ſaid, the way to get preferment and <hi>places</hi> is to write or <hi>rail</hi> againſt <hi>Luther,</hi> as <hi>Eccius Coccius, &amp;c.</hi> found it, <hi>Pauper Lutherus multes ficit divites,</hi> ſo do many <hi>Mony Merchants,</hi> and <hi>Mercenarians,</hi> ſee it at this day, the way to get <hi>prefermeus</hi> is to be forward againſt us and the poor deſpiſed <hi>Remnant.</hi> Now, my Lord, let not your ear be open to all their <hi>lies,</hi> and not once open to the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of <hi>Truth</hi> on our ſide. will you be pleaſed to peruſe a little thoſe writings taken out of my <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>udy,</hi> and ſatisfie your <hi>ſelf</hi> concerning the truth of them, <hi>oculo irretorto,</hi> and not beleeve thoſe <hi>bits</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:125687:8"/>and <hi>parts,</hi> which ſome <hi>Sycophants;</hi> probably, will acquaint you with, on purpoſe to irritate and inrage you againſt the <hi>truth,</hi> and <hi>Aſſerters</hi> of it. Too too many ſuch <hi>Flatterers</hi> are about you my Lord! which makes our hearts to <hi>bleed</hi> for you! that <hi>juſtific the wicked for reward, and take away the righteenſneſſe of the righteous from him, Iſayah</hi> 5th But if we have no hopes left to prevail with you, yet our heares are filled with hopes, and ſure we are to prevail with <hi>God;</hi> our <hi>Appeal</hi> is in heaven, and the faith and prayer; which are up, (as high as ever ſince the world ſtood) either will bring forth your <hi>converſion;</hi> for <hi>Luther</hi> ſaith the Church converts, <hi>totun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundum ſanguins &amp; oratione,</hi> or your <hi>confuſion.</hi> For the death and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the <hi>Perſecutors,</hi> was as it was ſaid of the death of <hi>Arrius, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cationis opus non morbi.</hi> But if it be asked, what we would have you do, our preſent or <hi>Anſwer</hi> is; firſt <hi>adviſe</hi> with the Lord by faith and prayer, about <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> your former <hi>Declarations,</hi> and the good <hi>peoples</hi> expectations in your Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet a little) for it is ſaid of <hi>Carelus Magnus</hi> (oh that the like might be ſaid of you!) <hi>Plus cum Deo quam cum hominibus lequitur,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> he loves more to be taking with <hi>God</hi> then with <hi>men,</hi> or any of his Court. 2. And then <hi>Proclaime Faſt</hi> or <hi>ſolemae day</hi> of <hi>humiliation</hi> for the <hi>errors</hi> and <hi>ſins paſt,</hi> as 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21.27.29. it came to paſſe <hi>when Ahab heard thoſe words he rent his clothes and faſted, and lay in ſack cloth, &amp;c.</hi> and <hi>the Lord ſaid, ſeeſt thou how</hi> Ahab <hi>humbleth himſelfe, becauſe he humbleth himſelfe before me I will not bring the evill in his dayes. And in</hi> 1 Sam. 12.19. <hi>The people ſaid,</hi> Samuel <hi>pray for thy ſervants unto the Lord thy God that we dye not, for wee have added unto all our ſins this</hi> evill, <hi>to aske a King, and why was this ſo great a ſinne?</hi> ſee <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.5. <hi>they ſaid make us a King, like as all the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions about us have) And the Lord ſaid,</hi> verſ. 7. <hi>They have not rejected thee but they have rejected me, that I ſhould not Reign over them;</hi> this was their <hi>great ſin,</hi> ſeeing the Lord himſelfe would have <hi>ruled</hi> them, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceived the alone <hi>Abſolute Government</hi> over them, upon which account <hi>Gideon</hi> (good man) refuſed it) <hi>Iudges</hi> 8.23. ſaying. <hi>I will not rule ever you, but the Lord ſhall rule ever you,</hi> 3. Furthermore, let a <hi>ſolemn day</hi> and duty be ſet apart to ſeek the Lord, for advice and <hi>Councell</hi> what to doe; which <hi>good Princes</hi> and <hi>people</hi> alwayes did upon <hi>ſtraits</hi> and <hi>emurgencies</hi> of old, as <hi>Iudg.</hi> 7.23.27. <hi>ſhall we goe forward or ceaſe</hi> (ſay they) ſo 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20 3. <hi>Iehoſaphat feared, and ſet himſelfe to ſeek<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Lord, did proclaimed a Faſt throughout Iudah:</hi> ſo <hi>Ezra</hi> 8.23. the want of this makes ſo much <hi>complaint</hi> by the Lord, as in <hi>Amos</hi> 6.13. <hi>Yee rejoyce in a thing of nought ſaying, have we not taken to us horus by our own ſtrength?</hi> And <hi>Hoſea</hi> 8 4 <hi>They have ſet up Kings but not by me, and Princes and I know it not, that it without</hi> ſo much as <hi>asking</hi> it at my hands, or conſulting with my word, or my Seers (as they ſhould doe) but of their owne <hi>heads</hi> they have done this. Therefore let the Lord be ſought to about theſe things,<note place="margin">What to be done in order to return</note> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing other things were <hi>juſtly expected</hi> from them that <hi>profeſſed</hi> Chriſt; but the <hi>Summer</hi> is ended, yea the <hi>Harveſt</hi> is paſt and we are not refreſhed! O my Lord! truſt not to ſuch <hi>Flatterers</hi> as alwayes ſpeak <hi>ſmooth Things</hi> to you, and propheſie <hi>deceitfully;</hi> O hear a little the Lords own Seers! <hi>via.</hi> the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the <hi>Vnction</hi> from an High<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>. And therefore let out
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:125687:9"/>the Lords Priſoners (whom the Churches are robbed of) <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Feak</hi> and Mr. <hi>Simpſon</hi> &amp; that they may open to you <hi>the preſent viſion</hi> of God given them in theſe things! according to the <hi>diſpenſation</hi> of the <hi>ſpirit!</hi> O hear them! once (at laſt) preach to you in the power of <hi>Ieſus;</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or whom (alone) they ſuffer, infirmities excepted, and by the word of the Lord try the <hi>ſpirit</hi> whither of God or no? for we are perſwaded as long as they be in <hi>Priſon</hi> you will be in blindneſs to the Truth, <hi>(Tanquam ad doctrinam peregrinam)</hi> Therefore let them have though but for a moneth or two, and though but half ſo much Liberty, to open <hi>the word of the Lord</hi> to you, as your Chaplains have, if they preach not the very <hi>Truth,</hi> and prove it to be ſo before all men impriſon them again,<note place="margin">Let out the Lords priſoners M. Feak M. Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Han. Trapnal now in Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel for Chriſt.</note> &amp; us too with them in this cauſe; though hitherto we may ſay, as <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid, <hi>Fideliter praedicare nihil alind eſt quam furorem mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di in ſe derivare,</hi> our <hi>Faithful</hi> preaching hath <hi>raiſed</hi> up <hi>fury</hi> againſt us. O my Lord! think of theſe things; theſe are the ſwords that <hi>pierce</hi> thorow our very ſouls, we ſue not for our own lives, but for yours herein; did not <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſend for <hi>Ioſeph</hi> out of priſon, to interpret his dream? <hi>Gen.</hi> 41. and <hi>Belſhaſſar</hi> ſend for <hi>Dan. chap</hi> 5. to open his viſion, yea and preferd him too, though <hi>Daniel</hi> declared his ruine, <hi>according to viſion;</hi> Surely, ſurely, you wil find it then, the <hi>wiſdom</hi> of <hi>God</hi> is more excellent then the <hi>arts &amp; ſciences of the wiſe men about you.</hi> But if you wil yet go on, <hi>adexitium potius quam ad exercitium,</hi> after all our bleeding intreaties, and be hardned up by the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous <hi>counſel</hi> of your own <hi>Reaſon</hi> or <hi>them</hi> about you, then my Lord, our ſouls ſhal <hi>mourn</hi> in ſecret for you, as for one deſperately loſt indeed, and we ſhal proceed to bear our teſtimony againſt the ſins of the times; for our ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals hangs in heaven, and we cannot recall it, yea as <hi>Luther</hi> once ſaid, <hi>Quo magis illi furunt eo amplius precede,</hi> the more men <hi>rage,</hi> the more reſolute we hope to be in our <hi>Appeals</hi> ſaith &amp; prayer to our <hi>JEHOVAH,</hi> continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up the Altar <hi>ED</hi> for a <hi>witneſs,</hi> between us and our <hi>Adverſaries;</hi> yea &amp; come if need be as the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> did by <hi>whole Troops</hi> to <hi>Arrius Antonious</hi> proclaiming themſelves Chriſtians,<note place="margin">Our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution</note> and offering themſelves up to the death for the <hi>Truth:</hi> Being aſſured in our very ſouls, though we now mourn we ſhall <hi>rejoice</hi> with joy unſpeakable and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ull of glory, <hi>Luctus in laetitiam convertetur, lachrymae in riſum, ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cus in ſericum cineres in corellas &amp; ungu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entum, jejunium in epulum, et <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anuum retortio in applauſum,</hi> In the meantime I beſeech you <hi>my Lord</hi> pardon <hi>infirmities,</hi> for <hi>God</hi> hath <hi>pardon'd them,</hi> &amp; own what <hi>God</hi> owns, that's <hi>truth:</hi> For <hi>potius in ardentem regum in ſiluere, quam ullum peccatum in deum commiſero,</hi> as one ſaid, I had rather, <hi>the Lord knows I think,</hi> leap into a bonfire, then wilfully commit wickedneſſe or ſin againſt God, yea <hi>mallem obedire quam miracula facere,</hi> as <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid, I had rather <hi>be obedient to my God then work miracles,</hi> and ſurely my Lord, will you be a little ſerious, you will ſay that it is <hi>Conſcience</hi> to our duty which doth altogether prompt us to this preſent <hi>conteſt,</hi> for the <hi>truth, Cauſe,</hi> and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of our dear Lord Ieſus the King of <hi>Saints,</hi> and <hi>Nations,</hi> wherein I am heartily deſirous, to be ready to live or die, which my Maſter, whom I ſerve will have me herein, without the leaſt tit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le or compound of Fraud, or Flattery. So far as I may,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your True Sincere Servant, <hi>JOHN ROGERS.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
